Guide to the William Grabowski Photographs 1980s, 2004-2022 PR 321
New-York Historical Society
William Grabowski photographs
1985-88, 2004-2022 (bulk, 2014-2021)
New-York Historical Society
Grabowski, William, 1954-
PR 321
14 Linear feet in 8 flat boxes
The William Grabowski photographs consist of about 1,160 color prints of digital snapshots of New York City, primarily Manhattan, Queens, and Brooklyn, taken mostly between 2014 and 2021. Especially well-represented in the collection are images of graffiti art/murals in Bushwick, Brooklyn and at 5 Pointz in Long Island City, Queens; street performers, theater marquees, and other scenes from the Times Square/Theater District; winter holiday decorations and events such as the Holiday Train Show and the illuminated residences of Dyker Heights, Brooklyn; and a broad range of structures around the city, especially museums, corporate towers, bridges, parks, churches, etc., with some skyline views.
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of William Grabowski, 2012 (28 photographs), 2014-2016 (319 photographs), 2017 (393 photographs), 2018 (117 photographs), 2019 (204 photographs), 2020 (87 photographs), 2021 (14 photographs), and 2022 (2 photographs) for a total of 1164. A second person collaborated with William Grabowski on some of the photographs; these are noted at the folder level.
Biographical Note
William Grabowski (1954- ) was born in Rego Park, Queens and later moved to Suffolk County on Long Island. He studied art as an undergraduate at SUNY Stonybrook, and received an Master of Science degree in secondary education from Hofstra University, and an Master of Science degree in instructional technology from Long Island University at CW Post. An art teacher in public schools for nearly 40 years, Grabowski also involved himself with local and regional arts councils. His artwork encompasses a variety of media, including photography, collage, and painting.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection consists of about 1,160 color prints of digital snapshots of New York City. The prints are typically 19 inches x 13 inches. All five of the city's boroughs are represented in the photographs, especially Manhattan (530 photographs), Brooklyn (268), and Queens (205). The bulk of the photographs were taken from 2014-2021; two are from the 1980s and a few range from 2004-2012 and 2022. Each image was labeled with a title and date by the photographer.
One dominant emphasis of the photographs is New York's built environment. This is found in exterior views of a wide range of buildings and other structures: museums, Broadway theaters (especially marquees), sports stadiums (specifically, Yankee Stadium and the Mets' Citifield), bridges, corporate towers, airports (especially JFK), churches, and others. Several of these photographs have a skyline orientation, rather than a focus on a particular building. The photographs are generally of exteriors.
Many of the photographs are of particular unique, often transient, details found on these buildings. The marquees of theaters announcing the production showing at the time is one example. Another are the extensive sets of photographs of street art/murals found throughout the city. The murals of 5 Pointz in Queens (destroyed in 2013-14), at Bushwick Collective in Brooklyn, at Welling Court in Queens, and the Audubon Mural Project in Harlem are well-represented in the collection. There are photographs of the Christmas holiday decorations of residences in Brooklyn's Dyker Heights neighborhood. Sets of photographs taken at the 2017 and 2020 Holiday Train Show at the New York Botanical Garden provide close-ups of many of the replica miniatures of buildings shown at the event.
Although pedestrians and street life are not major subjects found throughout the collection, one exception to this is the Times Square area. There are many photographs that capture the flavor of the area, from street vendors to the character actors to the crowds to the surrounding buildings and large-scale signage. The Pride March of 2017, Women's March of 2017, street fairs in Queens, and other such events are also included to a limited extent. There are a small number of photographs of homeless or panhandling individuals.
Finally, parks and other places of relative quiet in the city appear, such as those of Central Park, the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, Pratt Institute's outdoor sculptures, Flushing Meadow Park, Roosevelt Island, and others.
Accruals
The collection is open for additional donations from William Grabowski.
Arrangement
The photographs are organized in seven series, representing New York City's five boroughs plus two series for photographs not related to any particular borough.
Series I. Manhattan (530 photographs)
Series II. Bronx (73 photographs)
Series III. Brooklyn (268 photographs)
Series IV. Queens (205 photographs)
Series V. Staten Island (13 photographs)
Series VI. Bridges, Tunnels & Ferries (57 photographs)
Series VII. Statue of Liberty & Ellis Island (18 photographs)
Within each series, the photographs are organized by general subject. The series and subject categorizations were established by the processing archivists to facilitate access to the hundreds of photographs. The photographer labeled all photographs with a file name based on the specific subject and (often) the year/month of the image.
Bridges -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Public institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Public spaces -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Street art -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Queens (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Color photographs.
- Series I: Manhattan, 1985-1988, 2005-2022 (bulk, 2014-2021)
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds about 530 photographs taken in the New York City borough of Manhattan. About 160 of these photographs are of the Times Square and Theater District area. These images primarily include the theater's marquees and street performers/character actors in the area, but also include the buildings, signs, vendors, and other scenes representative of Times Square in these years (2014-2020).
  Manhattan's built environment dominates the photographs. In addition to the Times Square/theaters, photographs focus on either particular buildings (e.g., churches, museums, corporate towers) or take a broader, skyline view. About 77 photographs move away from the borough's more imposing structures to include parks (mostly Central Park), memorials, statues, and a set of photographs from the far west side of Greenwich Village.
  Street art/graffiti/murals appear in the series, in about 60 photographs. 14 of these are of the Audubon Mural Project in Harlem. Some events are represented in the series with a few photographs each, including Christo's installation of "The Gates" in Central Park (2005), Pope Francis's appearance in Central Park (2015), the Women's March (2017), and a Pride March (2017). The two earliest photographs in the collection, from 1985 and 1988, are in the events category; these are scenes from the Jacques d'Amboise Event of the Year at the National Dance Institute.
  The container list provides a more detailed summary for each folder.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged alphabetically by general subject matter, then chronologically within subject. The number of photographs in each folder is noted in parentheses in the container list.
  - Art. Street Art / Graffiti / Murals (5), 2011-2014 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Chelsea, Chinatown.
  - Art. Street Art / Graffiti / Murals (10), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
    From the Bowery, Greenwich Village,and Lower East Side.
  - Art. Audubon Mural Project (14), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
  - Art. Street Art / Graffiti / Murals (26), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 9-10)
    From upper Manhattan, Harlem, Midtown, subway walls, Soho, Greenwich Village, and lower Manhattan.
  - Art. Street Art / Graffiti / Murals. City as School High School (5), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 11)
  - Art. Street Art / Graffiti / Murals (1), 2022 (Offsite-box 8)
    One photo of a mural in Hell's Kitchen.
  - Bohemian National Hall (4), 2018 March (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    One exterior, three interiors
  - Buildings. Various (18), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    Chrysler Building (at night), Citicorp, Freedom Tower, American Geographical Society, Federal Hall, New York Stock Exchange, American Stock Exchange, Friars Club, Columbus Circle, Bohemian National Hall, Thompson Arts Center at Park Avenue Armory, Chelsea Piers, Brookfield Place, Empire State Building (at dusk, with holiday lights), Grand Central Terminal, and other views.
  - Buildings. Various (14), 2018, 2020 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 8)
    2018: Overpass to Grand Central Terminal at Pershing Square (2018, 2020, firefighters at 5th Avenue building after a steam explosion, New York City Visitors Center (exterior), Brill Building (exterior), Copacabana and storefronts, Edison Ballroom marquee and building above, Radio City Music Hall marquee, Salmagundi Club interior and exterior, billboard for Santa Margherita prosecco at the Midtown Tunnel. 2020: New York Public Library, 42nd Street entrance; Jadite Galleries; Trump International Hotel.
  - Buildings. Various (13), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Includes Salmagundi Club (1 exterior, 2 interior); St. Regis; Manhattan Center for Science and Mathematics (2); Chrysler Building; Trump complex and Riverside Boulevard in upper Manhattan; Gatsby Hotel; New York University Steinhardt Building; Plaza Hotel; Steinway Tower under construction; Trump Park Avenue entrance.
  - Buildings. Various (1), 2022 (Offsite-box 8)
    One photo of a closed souvenir shop (Covid-19 impact) in Midtown West.
  - Buildings. Churches (8), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    Holy Name of Jesus, Heavenly Rest, St. Bartholomew Episcopal, Trinity, St. Paul's Chapel, Church of the Intercession, St. Luke Lutheran, Church of Scientology.
  - Buildings. Penn Station, Madison Square Garden, and Farley Post Office/Penn Station Annex (6), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Farley Post Office exterior, with Penn Station Annex at right (1), interior main level (1) and lower level (1), steps up from subway platforms (1), Madison Square Garden entrances at 7th Avenue (2).
  - Events (17), 1985-1988; 2005-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    2 photos from circa 1985 and circa 1988: Jacques d'Amboise Event of the Year, National Dance Institute. Others: Pope and crowds at Central Park (the three images of the Pope event were created by Grabowski with Alexa Ruffino); scenes of city after blizzard of 2016; Christo's "The Gates" in Central Park (2005).
  - Hudson Yards (4), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    Includes one of The Vessel, 2 of the waterfront, and one of the "Edge" from below.
  - Lower Manhattan (7), 2020 (Offsite-box 8)
    Includes Brookfield Place (5), including ice rink, North Cover Marina, and atrium with palm trees; One World Trade Center; and view from promenade across Hudson River to Jersey City.
  - Marches / Parades (10), 2017, 2020 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Women's March on Fifth Avenue, 21 January 2017 (2). Pride March, 25 June 2017 (7). Wage theft/anti-Governor Cuomo protest (February 2020).
  - Monuments and Statues (5), 2014-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    American Merchant Mariners; Korean War; Washington Square Arch.
  - Monuments and Statues (7), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 14)
    Includes 7th Regiment (in Central Park), Washington Square Arch, Duffy Square statue, and Battery Park area: Castle Clinton, Pier 1, Merchant Marine, and Korean War Memorial.
  - Museums (16), 2004-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Whitney; view of Hoboken from Whitney; Ellis Island (exterior, interiors, tile details, etc.); Metropolitan Museum of Art; Cloisters; Cooper Union Museum; New-York Historical Society; Salmagundi Club; Discovery Times Square (Star Wars exhibits).
  - Museums and Galleries (9), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    New-York Historical Society front (3) and lamp post signage for Kalinsky/Muhammad Ali exhibition. National Academy Museum, "Museum Mile" street sign, Metropolitan Museum of Art front entrance, Neue Galerie banner.
  - Museums (1), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    American Museum of Natural History 77th street entrance
  - Parks and Gardens (14), 2006-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Central Park, "Imagine" memorial, fireworks, Great Lawn concert crowd, horse-drawn carriage, etc. (including two color infrared photos); Washington Square Park; High Line.
  - Parks and Memorials (9), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 7)
    National September 11 Memorial fountain (2). High Line at West 20th street (1). Roosevelt Island (6): Franklin D. Roosevelt Four Freedoms Park, smallpox hospital, Strecker Memorial Laboratory.
  - Parks. Central Park (12), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 8)
    Performer creating giant bubbles, John Purroy Mitchel memorial, Reservoir with east view/skyline, Bow Bridge, Bridge 24, Bridge 28, Tavern on the Green entrance, horse drawn carriage, "Imagine" memorial at Strawberry Fields, Lake with west side skyline, Bethesda Terrace and Fountain.
  - Parks (6), 2018 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 7)
    One of Bryant Park, rest of Central Park: hansom cab, musicians performing, 7th Regiment Memorial, Giuseppe Mazzini Memorial, Tavern on the Green entrance.
  - Parks. Little Island (7), 2021 (Offsite-box 8)
    7 photographs of the park at Pier 55 on the Hudson River waterfront, taken in August 2021 shortly after the park's opening in May 2021.
  - Restaurants (10), 2009-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Tavern on the Green (interiors, exteriors, barricaded after it closed in, 2009); Bobby Van's; Hard Rock Cafe; Sardi's.
  - Schools and Colleges (1), 2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    New York University Rubin Residence Hall
  - Skyline (14), 2009-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
    Primarily view of Manhattan skyline from various angles. Some focus on particular structures, including Empire State Building and 423 Park Avenue. Also includes Jersey City/Ellis Island view, view across Calvary Cemetery, view into Central Park.
  - Skyline (9), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 9)
    Photographs taken from across the East River, featuring the mid and upper east side of Manhattan, including United Nations, Presbyterian Weill Cornell, Rockefeller University, and a Circle Line ship on the East River with Citicorp and other buildings in background.
  - Skyline (3), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 12)
    Midtown (Chrysler building and north) skyline (from the east)
  - Street Performers (15), 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Times Square (Naked Cowboy, Naked Cowgirl, "painted ladies," Mickey Mouse and other characters, Statue of Liberty mimes); Washington Square Park dancers; Central Park musician in costume.
  - Street Performers (1), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Performers dressed as Statue of Liberty being photographed with costumed visitor.
  - Street Views - General (22), 2005-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10.1-10.2)
    Views of streets (and some street life) and buildings from street level: Freedom Tower, Cupcake ATM, street vendors, Flatiron Building, Christie's, street sign for 6-1/2 Avenue, Brookfield Place, Battery Park City, Greenwich Village townhouse, FDR Drive, Chelsea Pier, Columbus Circle, others.
  - Street Views- Holiday Decorations (5), 2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Rockefeller Center, Macy's, others.
  - Theaters. Various (34), 2014-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13.1-13.2)
    Marquees: Radio City, Cort ("Bright Star"), August Wilson ("Jersey Boys"), Schubert ("Matilda"), Ed Sullivan ("Late Show with Stephen Colbert"), Winter Garden ("School of Rock"), Ambassador ("Chicago"), Walter Kerr ("Crucible"), Lunt-Fontanne ("Finding Neverland"), Palace ("An American in Paris"), Minskoff ("Lion King"), St. James ("Something Rotten"), Richard Rodgers ("Hamilton"), Majestic (Phantom of the Opera"), Helen Hayes ("The Humans"). Interiors: Majestic, O'Neill, Carnegie Hall, David Koch Theater, "Nutcracker" at Lincoln Center. 42nd Street view. Lincoln Center Plaza. "Solar Reserve" artwork at Lincoln Center. Oother signage.
  - Theaters. Lincoln Center (12), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
    Entrances/signage to Tisch WNET Studios, David Geffen Hall, and Alice Tully Hall. Interior views of David Koch Theater. Cast of "Firebird on stage. Curtain call and finale of "Nutcracker."
  - Times Square (13), 2014-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Duffy Square, TKTS, vendors, signage, One Times Square Building, Hershey's store, others.
  - Theater District and Times Square (11), 2017 July (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    Marquees: Music Box ("Dear Evan Hansen"), Minskoff ("Lion King"), Booth. Times Square Disney store, Hershey store, buildings, signs, Duffy Square, street performers in costume, "painted ladies."
  - Theater District and Times Square (19), 2017 September (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
    Marquees: Schubert ("Hello Dolly," with Bette Midler), Broadhurst ("Anastasia"), Lunt-Fontanne ("Charlie and the Chocolate Factory"), Majestic ("Phantom of the Opera"), Imperial ("Carousel"), Schoenfeld ("Come From Away"), Booth ("Meteor Shower"). Birdland entrance, Sardi's restaurant (1 interior with autographed caricatures on wall, 1 exterior); Statue of Liberty made of Lego blocks, building mural, Times Square signs, street performers in character costumes, "painted ladies," homeless man sleeping on sidewalk, street vendor/hats.
  - Theater District and Times Square (8), 2017 November (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
    Marquees: Lunt Fontanne ("Charlie and the Chocolate Factory"), Barrymore ("The Band's Visit"), Brooks Atkinson ("Waitress"), Richard Rodgers ("Hamilton"), Booth ("Meteor Shower"), Schoenfeld ("Come From Away"), Don't Tell Mama piano bar. Marriott Marquis exterior elevators.
  - Times Square (20), 2018 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 9)
    The photographs in this folder are principally of people in Times Square: street performers (dancers, musicians), vendors, panhandlers, costumed performers (Statue of Liberty, Pikachu, Mickey Mouse, Minnie Mouse, Hulk), "Naked Cowboy," "Naked Cowgirl," caricature artist, China political protesters at TKTS booth, man carrying "Shine for Jesus" sign.
  - Theater District and Times Square (16), 2018 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 10)
    Marquees: St. James ("Frozen"), Shubert ("Hello Dolly" with Bernadette Peters), Imperial ("Carousel"), Barrymore ("The Band's Visit"), Manhattan Theatre Club ("Saint Joan"), Brooks Atkinson ("Waitress"), Longacre ("A Bronx Tale"), Ambassador ("Chicago"), Eugene O'Neill ("The Book of Mormon"), Ed Sullivan ("The Late Show with Stephen Colbert"), Lunt-Fontanne ("Summer: The Donna Summer Musical"), Lyceum ("The Play That Goes Wrong"). Interiors: St. James, Imperial. Wide angle view of West 45th Street with Booth ("Boys in the Band"), Schoenfeld ("Come From Away"), and other theaters.
  - Theater District and Times Square (16), 2018 June (Offsite-box 6, Folder 11)
    Times Square signage for theaters, etc.; Duffy Square steps/bleachers (from various angles); street signage for Broadway and George Abbott Way intersection with security camera; Sardi's restaurant (exterior and interior); views from the elevator and upper floor restaurant of the Marriott Marquis (9).
  - Theaters and Theater District (12), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 13)
    Marquees:Apollo, CBS Broadcast Center, Ziegfeld, Richard Rodgers ("Hamilton"), Cort ("Secret"), New York City Ballet. Interior of Shoenfeld and cast ("Come From Away") (3). Audience and set of "The View" (2). Stage performance at Radio City Music Hall of Ben Platt.
  - Theaters and Theater District (2), 2020 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 12)
    42nd Street marquees and signage; Playwrights Horizons theater
  - Transportation (9), 2016-2017 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    2016 (5): Taxi (interior), Penn Station (entrance, hallway, LIRR ticket booth), Circle Line boat (detail). 2017 (4): a Citibike stand, bus in Chinatown with advertising aimed at people of Asian heritage for Bally's casino in Atlantic City, doubledecker tour buses.
  - Transportation (5), 2019 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 15)
    Includes cars on Henry Hudson Parkway, Citibikes (parked), horse drawn carriages (2), doubledecker sightseeing bus.
  - Upper West Side (10), 2018 November (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    Veterans Day Parade (2), Central Park West food cart vendors (2), signage for New-York Historical Society's "Harry Potter" exhibition and "Harry Potter and the Cursed Child" Broadway play (2), Theodore Roosevelt equestrian statue and holiday dinosaurs at front of American Museum of Natural History (3), fall decorations at townhouse entrance (1).
  - West Greenwich Village (14), 2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
    Washington Square Arch (one daytime image and two night images, the latter including artist Ai WeiWei's "Good Fences Make Good Neighbors" temporary public art installation), Alexander Holley sculpture, Greenwich House entrance, Stonewall National Monument, General Sheridan statue, Duplex cabaret (exterior), St. Veronica Church, Big Gay ice cream shop, Hudson River Park, entrance to Christopher street PATH station, Northern Dispensary.
- Series II: Bronx, 2009, 2015-2020
  The series includes 73 photographs taken in the New York City borough of the Bronx. The bulk of these, a total of 55, were taken in December 2017 and in 2020 at the Holiday Train Show at New York Botanical Garden and are close-ups of many of the show's miniature replicas of famous New York City structures. There are also five photographs of Yankee Stadium and seven of the Wave Hill grounds and buildings, among other subjects. The container list provides a more detailed summary for each folder.
  - Holiday Train Show at New York Botanical Garden (31), 2017 December (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1A)
    Close-ups of many of the miniature replicas of famous New York City structures such as the Enid A. Haupt Conservatory, Penn Station, George Washington Bridge, Cyclone roller coaster, Chrysler building, etc., made of bark, leaves, and other natural materials.
  - Holiday Train Show at New York Botanical Garden (24), 2020 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1B)
  - Street Views (3), 2015 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    View on Bronx River Parkway, view on Cross Bronx Expressway, man with sign panhandling.
  - Yankee Stadium (5), 2009, 2017 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    Interior of seating, field, and from under the facade (2009); one exterior from behind fencing (2017).
  - Bronx Zoo (3), 2016 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    Entrance, zebra, and peacock with other animals.
  - Wave Hill (7), 2018 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    Entrance gate, conservatory interior, Great Lawn, Wave Hill House and Glyndor Gallery exteriors, signage at Riverdale Ave and 254th Street.
- Series III: Brooklyn, 2005, 2015-2020
  The series includes 268 photographs taken in the New York City borough of Brooklyn. 166 of these images are of street art/murals, primarily from the Bushwick neighborhood, including from the Bushwick Collective. Another 21 photographs, some co-created by Holly and William Grabowski, are of holiday decorations and lights on Dyker Heights residences (December 2017 and 2020).
  Other photographs include Pratt Institute (especially of the outdoor sculpture on the grounds), Brooklyn Botanic Garden (including cherry blossoms), Coney Island, and others.
  - Art. Graffiti / Street Art / Murals (58) (4 folders), 2015-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10-13)